<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-01T18:35:55+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ed’s Blog</title><subtitle>A personal blog where I&apos;ll write stuff and things</subtitle><author><name>Edmund Steele</name></author><entry><title type="html">Western Japan - Onomichi and Shikoku</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/japan/2024/10/30/western-japan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Western Japan - Onomichi and Shikoku" /><published>2024-10-30T18:41:18+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-30T18:41:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/japan/2024/10/30/western-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/japan/2024/10/30/western-japan.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="omonichi">Omonichi</h2>

<p>My main reason for visiting this town was to do the ‘Shimanami Kodo’ a fun cycling route that links together the mainland of Honshu with the smaller and much more rural island of Shikoku. I’d say as a single activity this was the highlight of my holiday. Its hard really to overstate how awesome and how right up my street it was. You basically cycle through beautiful fishing villages and docks across these improbably massive suspension bridges. Onomichi is beautiful enough as is and I had probably my best Ramen experience in Japan here - the food was great and it was first place I was able to sound out a menu item by reading the Hiragan aloud. I was absolutely buzzing from that and the “Ramen Master” seemed genuinely happy a tourist said something in Japanese.</p>

<p>On a side note the handwritten menus are something I love about Japanese restaurants - they presumably are 
there because they chef just makes whatever they have ingredients before on a bit of a rota, the food is low-cost with 
no frills. I <em>wish</em> we had more dining options for healthier fast food that’s casual and friendly for eating alone, just somewhere between 
Maccies and an actual restaurant.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/onomichi-ramen.jpeg" alt="Ramen" /></p>

<p>The town itself is nice in and of itself although I didn’t spend that much time here</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/onomichi.jpeg" alt="Onomichi" /></p>

<p>Am I in Venice?
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/canal.jpeg" alt="Canal" /></p>

<h4 id="aside-japanese-economic-history">Aside: Japanese Economic History</h4>

<p>This is the one of the most visible symbols in Japan of the dangers of over building infrastructure - as so much of the economy and employment of Japan is taken up in construction which boomed during Japan’s postwar economic miracle the government wanted (or due to cronyisnm) to keep the gravy train rolling. At this point Shikoku already has a great road and rail bridge to its most densely populated region in Kagawa province. The economic case for building another set of extremely expensive road only bridges isn’t that strong.
 The case against is basically</p>
<ul>
  <li>Massive upfront capital investment that may have more efficient uses (even tax cuts in some circumstances that allow people to spend where they feel it improves their lives best)</li>
  <li>The big one: the upkeep bill which always dwarves the initial cost of construction. If the economic growth in the regions is less than the cost of maintenance then you’ve got a white elephant.</li>
</ul>

<p>So in some ways the ‘point’ of the <em>Shimano Kodo</em> is to get <em>someone</em> to use these damn bridges and bring some tourist investment to the area! And I’m all for it. In some ways the engineering <em>was</em> the touristic experience - the staggering scale and majesty of these basically empty bridges is staggering. That there’s just one of these after another after another defies belief. Hats off to Japan in the 1990s - you had an ambition and belief in progress we seem to have lost a little in the UK.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/big-bridges.jpeg" alt="BigBridgeLittleCar" /></p>

<h2 id="shimmy-shimano-kodo">Shimmy Shimano Kodo</h2>

<p>OK it’s the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Shimanami Kodo</code> but it sounds kind of similar to the bike brake system <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Shimano</code> so my brain kept correcting it. 
There’s not much more to say so here’s some photos</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/paraiso-2.jpeg" alt="Islands" />
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/pano-shimano.jpeg" alt="Panorama" /></p>

<p>There were even purpose built ramps up to the bridges!
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/ramp-timelapse.mov" alt="BridgeRamp" /></p>

<h2 id="kagawa-prefecture-takamtsu">Kagawa Prefecture: Takamtsu</h2>

<p>Takamatsu was a wonderful surprise - I only really saw it as a pit stop on the way to the “Iya Valley” which I’d seen online and looked really cool. There’s nothing too amazing about this place in and of itself but from Japanese people I’d heard things about the “Sanuki Udon” Buckwheat noodle dishes in this part of Japan. I loved these noodles - they’re basically big, extra chunky noodles in rich meaty broths. 
Just gooey carby deliciousness in a bowl - their Chinese cousins Xi’an style noodles also have a special place in my heart because I used to get them relatively often when I lived with my brother over the long periods of lockdown as a pick me up.</p>

<p>As for an actual tourist attraction the only place I really went to was the “Ritsurin Koen” garden - absolutely beautiful and a place that really speaks to the peaceful serenity (and inequality) of the Edo feudal era.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/Takamatsu.jpeg" alt="TakamatsuGarden" /></p>

<h3 id="cross-country-to-the-south-coast">Cross Country to the South Coast</h3>

<p>From here things really started to unravel a little. Really I have no-one to blame but myself - I just tried to cram <em>way</em> too much in. I should really have picked a base, probably either Takamtsu or Kochi and done day trips, or just planned a little better. Basically as a estimate for about 3 days I spent probably an equal amount of time travelling as I did actually doing touristic activities.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/shikoku-train.jpeg" alt="AverageTrainRide" /></p>

<p>Japan has wonderful public transport, Shikoku’s is still OK … but it is fundamentally an extremely rural area. What I was doing was a little mad - basically trying to get to one of the most rural and inaccessible parts of Japan for effectively a day trip. Mad. It <em>did</em> work and I <em>did</em> get some good photos … but man I should have budgeted more time for this place or just cut part of the trip.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/shikoku-population.png" alt="PopulationDensity" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/shikoku-tea.jpeg" alt="Teagrowing" /></p>

<p>So the guesthouse I was staying at in the middle of nowhere basically had no food nearby so I had boil in the bag noodles for dinner and breakfast, I was a little cold, starting to feel quite homesick and lonely having not really had a long conversation for a couple of days at this point. I think it was at this point it kind of twigged that this was a holiday from work - not some kind of mad experience accumulation trip. So instead of dashing off on some expedition I just hired a bike then cycled to a river and chilled out. I don’t know if it was exhaustion or some kind of Shinto mindfullness but I did just sit next to a river in the sun for like an hour just existing.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/shikoku-sign.jpeg" alt="overgrown" /></p>

<p>My reverie was broken abruptly when my phone pinged me (IIRC)</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Your flight departs Kochi Airport for Tokyo in 2 hours, checkin closed!</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Yabaie! I had somehow booked my flight on the wrong day - perhaps related to the timezone on the app I was using? Again no-one to blame but myself but damn…</p>

<p>No worries I thought. I can still get a bus to Osaka or Okayama then ride the Shinkansen back to Tokyo. After all its just money, fortunately I could afford it. I then decided to check my hotel in Kochi (which I was still interested in seeing) and saw that (thanks Booking) it was actually about 20km outside accessible only through busses. Yay. At this point I should have just cut my losses - gone back to Takamatsu, grabbed any hotel I could then gone back on the next day.</p>

<p>A strange abandoned tourist attraction?
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/shikoku-mine.jpeg" alt="AbandonedPlace" /></p>

<p>Instead I was like “whatever” I’ve got time I’ll just sit on the busses. So I got up, found the cafe I wanted to visit, and probably the nicest cafe lunch I’d had in Japan with some of the kindest people - an old couple running a takeaway cafe in their village with locally produced ingredients and home cooking. The old lady even showed be making an offering to their Inari, which I totally humiliated myself by thinking she was offering buckwheat when it was really some other type of grass which they got a good chuckle out of.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/delicious-meal.jpeg" alt="Lunch" /></p>

<p>So I pedalled back to the train, got to Kochi then tried to get to the hostel. The hostel owner was just unbelievably friendly and helpful - texting me and helping out with which bus to take, where to go etc. Unfortunately busses aren’t numbered and only have the Kanji of the end destination which, in my defence, is extremely confusing. Essentially I got on totally the wrong bus - the bus driver questioned where I was going then was like “Ie Ie, Kocchi (no no this way) -&gt;” pointing at some bus station (and not charging) then saying to go and ask the people inside for help. Which I did to the best of my ability I basically said</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>Me: Where village bus is?</p>

  <p>Ticket Person: What ??? I don’t understand</p>

  <p>Village … please ?</p>

  <p>…</p>

  <p>Excuse me, I’m sorry 
…</p>
</blockquote>

<p>I know I probably “did something wrong” but I’m sorry if you work in a bus station, and someone asks about a place what the hell do you think they are asking for? She knew, she was just being deliberately obstructive. I was stressed and a bit cranky which didn’t help but WTF was her problem? Just couldn’t be arsed I guess.</p>

<p>Anyway I figured out a route and managed to make it to the hostel but arrived long into the night, tired, hungry and about 2 hours late. I’m not ashamed to say that walking along the path of some fishing village and feeling the briny breeze and seaside smell of rotting kelp I was reminded of seaside holidays at home and I sat on the breakwater and had a little cry by myself in the dark. Not that I was sad or anything, just had to let something out. Fortunately the hostel owner was just the sweetest person, really friendly and kind. She even offered to drive me to the supermarket where I got some stir fry, salad and ice-cream and had a nice little meal using their microwave. The incredibly friendly shop counter guy may have thought we had a conversation but to this day I have no idea what he was talking about or why he thought I could speak Japanese, I was just nodding at appropriate times and smiling. He probably appreciated the company.</p>

<p>The next day started pretty well, I had a tasty breakfast of a seaweed rice ball then set off for Kochi. I’d fixed my route - there was a coach from Kochi (ahey) back to Okayama on the Shinkansen which would get me back to Tokyo (very expensively) on the same day. From there it all went downhill. I waited for the first bus, then waited some more, then some more, then the next busses supposed departure came and went then I started to stress. I was literally in the middle of nowhere, I didn’t know how to get a taxi or really how to get out easily. Instead I decided to hoof it overland to the next train station - about a 3 hour walk.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/neko.jpeg" alt="NekoCar" /></p>

<p>This is going to sound weird but a long country walk where you don’t want to do it, and its just an inconvenience hits totally different to a hike. In theory they’re both just nice long walks and there were literally tourists LARPing as pilgrims doing the same walk I was just so angry at myself for cocking this up as much as I had done. I think hitchhiking is illegal in Japan so I just walked. In some ways I’m glad I did because I saw non picturesque rural Japan and … it kind of sucks? 
It really did not feel like a wealthy place at all, perhaps a healthy and happy one but the houses were small and poor quality - lots of small scale labour intensive farming with the landscape churned up by ugly pavementless roads and tunnels. 
I’m not trying to be mean just understanding that actually its not that nice in the countryside to actually live - there’s lots of good reasons young people leave for the cities.</p>

<p>Still when I finally made it to the train station, sweaty and gross, and the train came and I arrived in Kochi I finally relaxed. There was a cool Sunday market which I just made to the end of where I got a nice cooking knife and some Matcha Tea Ice Cream and saw Kochi’s beautiful castle and gardens.</p>

<p><em>Aside: I learnt the morpheme for tea and think its really pretty</em></p>
<h1 id="茶-cha">茶 (cha)</h1>

<p>I worked out I’d spent about 8hrs travelling to get to Kochi and about 2 hours actually seeing the town. Leaving the place in probably the comfiest coach journey I’d ever taken (the driver even whispered the announcements to not disturb people!) I was just relieved.</p>

<p>Shikoku was probably the most min-maxed holiday I’ve ever had in my life. Elegiac wonder to depression with no in-between.</p>

<p>I’d definitely recommend it for hiking, cycling and sports and it was close to my favourite place to visit at its best but</p>
<ul>
  <li>Allow for a longer visit</li>
  <li>Hire a car</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/lying-flat-beach.jpeg" alt="LyingFlat" /></p>

<h3 id="musing">Musing</h3>

<p>I read somewhere that a tourist is defined as being someone “who travels to experience a change”. In that way 
I think Shikoku provided that for me. Its a bit odd in some ways to travel by yourself and I’m definitely feeling the 
terrifying progression of time and not really being young anymore. I actually think taking time to pause and reflect
while doing something totally out of the ordinary is a wonderful thing, and may even be the best thing about living
in a wealthy country for me.</p>

<p>Sleepy me except its dark and moody
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/west-japan/tired-me.jpeg" alt="TiredMe" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Edmund Steele</name></author><category term="japan" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Omonichi]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Central Japan: Nagoya, Kyoto and Osaka</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/japan/2024/10/29/central-japan.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Central Japan: Nagoya, Kyoto and Osaka" /><published>2024-10-29T18:41:18+00:00</published><updated>2024-10-29T18:41:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/japan/2024/10/29/central-japan</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/japan/2024/10/29/central-japan.html"><![CDATA[<h2 id="nagoya-is-not-boring">Nagoya (is not boring)</h2>

<p>For most people Nagoya is a station you pass through on the way between Tokyo and Kyoto, which is unfortunate because its actually quite nice. I wouldn’t go further than that - its like a cleaner, safer and more pleasant Birmingham. There’s not that much that you must do here, not really many historical sites or Instagramable photos. That being said though the castle is quite interesting, but again is a replica as the original was destroyed in an uprising in the 17th century against the Tokugawa.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/nagoya-castle-2.jpeg" alt="NagoyaCastle" /></p>

<p>For me the nicest thing was experiencing an everyday large Japanese city which receives very little tourism - even in such a big city you’d still get children staring because they see so few non-Japanese people then a very cute interaction of saying Konnichiwa to each other.</p>

<p>That being said the Toyota museum in the center of town was a really cool industrial history museum that’s worth checking out if you’re into engineering. Interestingly the museum was financed by the Toyota corporation so is essentially a propaganda/advertising piece. This meant most of the stuff you’d expect to find in a British museum about the downsides of industrialisation, the condition of the workers etc. was totally absent. It was just a parade of the impressive machines Toyota had built on their rise to global automotive dominance. There’s also a neat transport museum - its not <em>amazing</em> but worth checking out to learn more about the Shinkansen network.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/Shinkansen.jpeg" alt="Shinkansen" /></p>

<p>It was also quite fun walking around at night taking photos - there was also a national holiday the next day so there was a lively nighttime atmosphere for young Japanese people were out having fun. It’s also how noticeable wearing a camera gets you more looks than if you just walk around aimlessly - definitely a feeling that you must be somehow cooler or more interesting!</p>

<h2 id="kyoto-is-not-overtouristed">Kyoto (is (not) overtouristed)</h2>

<p>I slightly insanely only did a day trip to Kyoto which was mad because of how much stuff there was to see there, and how beautiful huge sections of the city were. I think I got put off by people saying how overtouristed and unpleasant it could be - but on the scale of a historic European city within 50km of an international airport it was nothing. The sites are ticketed often with timed entry so didn’t feel excessively busy - the busses were a great way to get around but you’ve got to stand most of the time.</p>

<p>I definitely regret not getting entry into the Imperial Palace because there was some impressive art and interiors, but in the back of my mind I know its not going anywhere and Japan might be a place I’d like to return to in decades to come.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/ImperialPalaceKyoto.jpeg" alt="KyotoPalace" /></p>

<p>A representation of not being able to see something nice
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/KyotoArt.jpeg" alt="KyotoArt" /></p>

<p>Kinkaku-Ji was impressive and the walk around the site was probably the most beautiful thing about it - in some ways not going in actually made it more mysterious and beautiful. Really through there is a one-way walk around the garden, but plenty of opportunities to get good photos and appreciate the beauty of the surroundings.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/GoldenRoofPlace.jpeg" alt="goldenplace" /></p>

<p>I should also state I actually used the Claude LLM to come up with itinerary which it did a fantastic job of repackaging other people’s travel blogs. It next suggested the ‘Geisha’ region of Kyoto - Gion. This was actually pretty but after the Post Towns it wasn’t that amazing to me.</p>

<p>The Inari Okami Tori gate procession is really cool. I went just before dusk and wow, I got people saying Kyoto was overtouristed. Basically 100s of people (at least) all arrived at once on trains and all went together through a long, dark narrow passageway - this was the only place that felt close to being dangerous with overcrowding. I could definitely see some pushing and fights the way people would just abruptly stop for selfies and try and chase people out of their shots. With that being said I chilled out and waited for darkness before going up by a back route which was actually extremely pleasant. I’m actually a fox fan so I really enjoyed seeing the <em>Kitsune</em>. I loved the Inari Okami lore - that foxes hunting in rice fields were the guardians of the rice, and also with bonus transformations into beautiful beguiling women.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/ToriGates.jpeg" alt="Tori" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/InariOkami.jpeg" alt="InariOkami" /></p>

<p>On my way down I saw a woman doing a photoshoot - hopefully this doesn’t count as an invasion of privacy - I just loved the lighting (shame about that stupid pole in the way)</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/KyotoPhotoshootLady.jpeg" alt="KyotoTradFemme" /></p>

<h2 id="osaka-is-ok">Osaka (is OK)</h2>

<p>Osaka was probably the place I regret visiting the most. Just to stress there’s absolutely nothing wrong with it and I’m sure its a nice place but it probably the only place I went to ‘just because’. I think its main draw is as a party/eating destination but as a solo tourist its kind of a lottery in who you meet as to how this pans out. Fortunately I did experience a nice Whisky bar with a dude from the hostel, but it was noticeable that everyone who walked through the door was a tourist. This was the case in a central zone as well - it <em>felt</em> like the most touristic place I visited, which was strange, especially after Kyoto and the Post Towns. Anyway I’ve got no great insights or experiences.</p>

<h4 id="night-photography-aside">Night Photography Aside</h4>

<p>This whole trip I definitely learned a tonne about photography and I really felt my photos improved. I’ll share a couple of night scenes here - I think I still wasn’t getting the exposure quite right - they’re probably more dark than really was happening but I was happy enough with the effect. The thing I found was after a couple of night/street photos they all start looking quite samey and strangely I found it hard to give the photos a sense of energy, at least that matched the energy and dynamism of a late evening street in a large Japanese city.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/central-japan/osaka-nigh-scenes.jpeg" alt="NightOsaka" /></p>]]></content><author><name>Edmund Steele</name></author><category term="japan" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nagoya (is not boring)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Matsumoto, Kamikochi and the Kiso Valley</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/japan,travel/2024/10/25/matusmoto-nakesendo.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Matsumoto, Kamikochi and the Kiso Valley" /><published>2024-10-25T19:41:18+01:00</published><updated>2024-10-25T19:41:18+01:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/japan,travel/2024/10/25/matusmoto-nakesendo</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/japan,travel/2024/10/25/matusmoto-nakesendo.html"><![CDATA[<p>In the Autumn of 2024 I visited Japan, which is an awesome place to visit and the first stop along the way I went to was Matsumoto, Kamikochi and the Kiso Valley.</p>

<p>Getting here from Tokyo was pretty straightforward, you can either get a bus or a train which both take about the same amount of time. I took the train because it was easier to fall asleep which I desperately needed after my long flight.</p>

<p>I think even after the whole trip Matsumoto might even have been my favourite place in Japan - I think the reasons were a (by Japanese standards) relaxed and laid back pace of life, beautiful surroundings and many old buildings surviving. It actually felt closest to a European Spa or Ski town, very chill and with some of the friendliest people I encountered in Japan.</p>

<p>The castle is probably the biggest draw if you’re just passing through, but I was mainly here to see the mountains.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/IMG_5941.jpeg" alt="MatsumotoCastleAtSunset" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/IMG_5872.jpeg" alt="MatsumotoCastleAtNight" /></p>

<p>It is quite unusual to have such a well preserved castle in Japan, both due to the Meiji era destruction of Japan’s feudal legacy, earthquakes and WW2 bombing so Matsumoto is one of the best ways to see a (mostly) original 17th century castle so close to Tokyo.</p>

<p>The Valley between the mountains</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/IMG_0698.jpeg" alt="MatsumotoValley" /></p>

<h3 id="kamikcohi">Kamikcohi</h3>

<p>Kamikochi is a mountain climbing and camping resort in some of Japan’s highest mountains. Its not really a town, more of a coach stop with some hotels used as a pit stop for hiking up the many mountain routes.</p>

<p>It’s extremely easy to do as a day trip from Matsumoto - you just go to the train station and buy a ticket. For some crazy reason you can’t buy a return and instead need to buy one when you get off the bus in Matsumoto (you go via a train then transfer to a bus). I think total it was about 8000 yen, which is £40 at the time I went which wasn’t unreasonable as its the main way for Kamikochi to make money off day trippers.</p>

<p>The Money Shot</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/IMG_5952.jpeg" alt="KamikochiValley" /></p>

<p>The hike I did with a couple of fit young guys was up Mount Yake Dake. I should stress this was totally doable as a day hike <em>if you are already very fit</em> if you’re not used to walking or are not so fit right now, or there’s adverse weather I would suggest not doing this. Even for us we found the ascent pretty tiring, and the downhill was a bit of a knee destroyer. That being said this was a fantastic hike and the views from the top, as well as the friendliness of the people there was so lovely. I’d like to thank the guy from the hostel who carried a coffee making kit all the way up and made us all some delicious black coffee - superstar!</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/IMG_5967.jpeg" alt="MountYakeDakeAscent" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/IMG_0765.jpeg" alt="MountYakeDakeSummit" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/ladders-yake-dake.jpeg" alt="Ladders" /></p>

<p>Back in Matsumoto there was even a bonus firework festival thrown which was free to enter with some live music and tasty food stalls which was a nice bonus! I was a little sad not to be able to spend more time there, but as a Japanese guy staying at the hostel pointed out there are mountains all over the world.</p>

<p>I would also really recommend <a href="https://www.couchpotatohostel.com/en/index.html">Couch Potato Hostel</a> as a place to stay with a lovely host and vibe.</p>

<h3 id="kiso-valleynakesendo">Kiso Valley/Nakesendo</h3>

<p>You can get to the Post Towns in the Kiso Valley very easily and pretty cheaply from Matsumoto. 
They’re definitely beautiful places but there’s not that much to do in them besides souvenir shopping. The history is that they were built to cater to travellers making the long walk between Kyoto and Edo/Tokyo in the Tokugawa Shogunate Era of Japan (1600-1850s).</p>

<p>Just based on hotel availability I stayed in a town called Nojiri on the path of the Nakesendo. At this point after several days of beautiful sunshine the weather turned extremely wet - wetter than anything I’d have experienced in the UK - just the force and the length of time it rained for were extremely unusual.</p>

<p>Staying in a more traditional hotel was pretty cool as well. 
<img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/Japanese%20Hotel.jpeg" alt="JapaneseRuralHotel" /></p>

<p>Still this random town provided an absolutely beautiful hike when I walked to Magome via Nagiso and Tsumago.</p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/Farming.jpeg" alt="RiceFarming" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/Bridges.jpeg" alt="WoodenBridge" /></p>

<p><img src="https://storage.googleapis.com/images-for-blog-ad4ea432-25af-4ea4-8d4b-58ea84408c68/photo-backups/twin-peaks.jpeg" alt="MistyMountains" /></p>

<p>I went an extremely long way - I was pretty much solidly walking from about 06:30 to 17:00 which was a little much, but the roads were mostly paved or very well maintained tracks so I made good progress. The wet weather got a little miserable - I mostly stayed dry enough but water pooled at the bottom of my backpack cover and made the inside wet. Be warned - prepare for absurd amounts of rainfall!</p>

<p>If I visited just one place I’d say Tsumago was my favourite post town, Magome got the most visitors wasn’t actually that beautiful and felt like it was straying into over-tourism with the extremely large numbers of tour groups. From a UK perspective it would be like going to Bibury in the Cotswolds - its not a fake village but it is just a living tourist trap.</p>

<p>Oh and the recommended hike of Magome -&gt; Tsumago at least when I did it was extremely busy - the photos of empty trails and pristine woodland are exaggerated. Not saying you wont get it, just that wasn’t my experience.</p>

<h3 id="in-summary">In summary</h3>

<p>This was an extremely approachable and fun outdoorsy start to the trip. Everything was pretty easy and with a bit of machine translation and sign language public transport was easy to navigate, reliable and fast. I don’t know if I’d recommend walking the whole Nakesendo as lots of Europeans were doing as there’s a lot of road walking seemingly but it was a cool thing to dip my toe into.</p>]]></content><author><name>Edmund Steele</name></author><category term="japan,travel" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In the Autumn of 2024 I visited Japan, which is an awesome place to visit and the first stop along the way I went to was Matsumoto, Kamikochi and the Kiso Valley.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">LLM’s will probably be a component of a truly intelligent system, not the system itself</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/software/2024/02/25/llms-need-a-source-of-truth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="LLM’s will probably be a component of a truly intelligent system, not the system itself" /><published>2024-02-25T18:41:18+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-25T18:41:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/software/2024/02/25/llms-need-a-source-of-truth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/software/2024/02/25/llms-need-a-source-of-truth.html"><![CDATA[<p>LLMs, while amazingly useful in so many ways, lack a concept of truth that will hold them back unless combined with a system capable of discerning true information from hallucinations.</p>

<h3 id="the-idea-of-hallucinations-is-a-marketing-gimmick">The idea of “hallucinations” is a marketing gimmick.</h3>

<p>There is no hallucination and there is no true output. A LLM produces whatever is statistically likely - in contrast a fact is not statistically likely, a fact simply is.</p>

<p>I’ve seen so many news reports that after listing the upside of an LLM will list the downsides, and will often list a “tendency to hallucinate” as a drawback. No. This isn’t something that can be fixed by the LLM itself. Take arithmetic - an early problem with ChatGPT was its failure to add numbers together. Thankfully this was fixed down this line by sending maths looking questions to an actual calculator. GPT didn’t ‘learn maths’; someone just added a subsystem to bypass the LLM where it was appropriate to. To fix maths in an LLM you’d need enough data covering enough arithmetic questions written in everyday language to be built into the model. Or you could just use existing arithmetic logic - something computers were built to do.</p>

<p>So this is a flawed example. No-one needs or wants AI to do arithmetic, that’s been a solved problem for decades now. Where we are currently seeing problems is a misapplication of AI into roles where truth is expected.</p>

<h3 id="llms-are-not-search-engines">LLMs are not search engines</h3>

<p>I used to work with a publishing company that provided services around analysing textual data for example providing a specialist search engine. While I worked in the grubby web development team, I sat across a row of desks for the data science team. This was before the AI explosion from 2021 onwards but they were of course well aware of the developments of GPT-2 - and for the most part they understood it to be a tool for a different problem. It was understood that when someone requested data relating to a certain topic or existing content they wanted … well content related to that topic or term. They didn’t want content that <em>might</em> relate to their query.</p>

<p>We’ve already seen a legal case thrown out because a lawyer trusted a response from an LLM about a non-existent case. In most cases I imagine we’re already seeing lower impact damage from researchers and analysts making mistaken conclusions from inaccurate but correct sounding output.</p>

<h3 id="llm-chatbots">LLM chatbots</h3>

<p>This is more likely to be a flash in the pan as companies will quickly realise their mistake in allowing ChatGPT free rein to help their customers. Personally I find AI chatbots exceedingly irritating but I’ll imagine that will improve as GPT slurps up more data. Recently an LLM put one statistically likely foot in front of the other and invented a refund policy that the parent company had to honour.</p>

<p>This is exceptionally silly. An LLM should never have been allowed to start generating text related to a refund policy. The overall system should have detected the customer was asking about refunds and stepped in with a deterministic print out of the company’s official refund policy and probably a number to call for a human. This would imply the existence of a second regulating system on top of GPT that checks and controls inputs and outputs from the internal GPT model to ensure they make sense.</p>

<h3 id="my-002">My $0.02</h3>

<p>So in these 3 examples we need a mind outside of GPT that can verify its responses. For now that’s us but does it have to be? Could we build a machine that is itself endogenously capable of somehow knowing what is true and what isn’t? If you’re a materialist then the answer clearly is yes - because we as biological machines can already do it. The question is how? I know actually - <em>but I’ll only tell you for 7 trillion USD!</em></p>

<p>For now I think the answer is always remembering to verify anything that sounds like a fact from GPT, and for software use cases wrapping the GPT input/output away from direct external usage and carefully controlling the communication through programmed rules. Someday this may look like an anachronism but for now although GPT will inevitably get better and better as it consumes more data, it can never know what it is saying is true.</p>]]></content><author><name>Edmund Steele</name></author><category term="software" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[LLMs, while amazingly useful in so many ways, lack a concept of truth that will hold them back unless combined with a system capable of discerning true information from hallucinations.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Things I’ve learnt as a self taught software developer</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/software/2024/02/18/what-id-tell-a-younger-me.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Things I’ve learnt as a self taught software developer" /><published>2024-02-18T09:41:18+00:00</published><updated>2024-02-18T09:41:18+00:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/software/2024/02/18/what-id-tell-a-younger-me</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/software/2024/02/18/what-id-tell-a-younger-me.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve now been a ‘self taught’ developer with 6 years professional experience. The process of reviewing graduate applications for my company has got me thinking about things that I’ve learnt coming into the industry and as I’ve gained more experience. I’ve got some groupings here that go beyond the non obvious stuff (know how to code)</p>

<h2 id="be-someone-people-want-to-work-with">Be someone people want to work with</h2>

<p>As a case study to illustrate this I’d like to talk about 2 people I’ve worked with previously. One was probably the best developer I’ve ever worked with, one was bang average. One rose through the ranks with amazing speed, one was borderline pushed out of their job. The difference? One of them was someone people liked working with.</p>

<p>To illustrate the point I had to visit Amsterdam to work for a period of time very early both in my career and in a new job, and I knew absolutely no-one there. Despite working in a totally different team Mr Soft Skills introduced himself and made sure to introduce me to the rest of the team (which my boss hadn’t bothered to do) took me to lunch and made sure I was settling in OK. It was genuinely such a small thing but the fact I still remember it so long after shows the impact these gestures can have. If everyone you work with has positive interactions like this with you it makes such a huge difference. This is something I personally sometimes struggle with - I’m quite proud and can sometimes get annoyed if condescended to or if dragged into something that’s not my responsibility.</p>

<h2 id="learn-the-theory">Learn the theory</h2>

<p>This is true if you haven’t done a CompSci or Software Engineering degree and is potentially true even if you have. While you’re starting a first job or as a junior it can be overwhelming so don’t always feel you have to work constantly. No-one ever expects you to immediately start producing like a senior developer but if you want to progress you will need to catch-up on things many of your colleagues will have learnt at university.</p>

<p>There’s some great resources out there, especially <a href="https://teachyourselfcs.com">TeachYourselfCS</a> and many free Youtube lecture series. In terms of importance my recommendations for areas of focus would be (from a BE developer perspective)</p>

<ol>
  <li>Learn another programming language in a different paradigm - e.g. if you know Python learn (some) Functional Programming, if you’ve only used Javascript learn some Java. This will stop you getting stuck in one way of thinking and broaden how you think about code in general.</li>
  <li>Databases - understand things like transaction isolation levels, broadly how query optimisation works and concurrency models. Schema design is very often the most critical part of application design, yet it is often overlooked by self taught developers.</li>
  <li>Algorithms and Data Structures. Initially this may seem like overkill but the wrong data structure choice can absolutely scupper an application.</li>
  <li>Networking - doesn’t have to be super in depth but knowing the basics of DNS/HTTP will serve you well in our distributed computing world.</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="dont-be-picky-for-your-first-job">Don’t be picky for your first job</h2>

<p>If you don’t have a CS degree or any proven experience getting a first job is rough, especially at the time of writing. My only experience of programming before I got a job was writing Data Science-esque code at university in Python. My first job was writing a Spring Java monolith for a small Insurance company in my hometown where I lived with my Mum.</p>

<p>Was it glamorous or prestigious? No. Did I like Java? Eh. Did I enjoy it? Sometimes. Was it good for my career? To an almost absurd degree yes.</p>

<p>When you start working you’ll learn far more than by teaching yourself, generally if you’re enthusiastic your fellow engineers will be more than happy to talk to you about anything and everything. I learnt so much about low level programming, how to help out with sales calls, how to work with product managers, the list goes on. This is almost impossible to self learn. I actually feel bad for ‘kids these days’ that are going to miss out on working in person and learning this stuff through osmosis but do what you can.</p>

<h2 id="make-mistakes-and-learn-from-them">Make mistakes and learn from them</h2>

<p>The most successful developers I’ve worked with have invariably been ones who have put themselves forward for new projects and suggested their own. At some point you need to make bold decisions yourself and suffer the consequences. I’ve been responsible for some disasters in my time, but really - looking back on them - they were fairly minor incidents that everyone else forgot about in a day or two.</p>

<p>I’ll tell you what though - experiments that pay off can be some of the most rewarding things you can do. They’re really a win-win: either your company gets a cool new feature or you learn for the rest of your career why something is a bad idea! (This depends on working somewhere that sees problems as a learning experience and not a stick to beat someone with)</p>

<h2 id="you-are-not-your-code">You are not your code</h2>

<p>Negative feedback on code submissions can be upsetting but never take it personally. Fundamentally you are making a product for a company - it’s never ‘yours’. There’s nothing more frustrating than a Junior Developer defending crazy design decisions because they can’t bear to be ‘wrong’. Of course some PR reviewers can be nasty. I hope you don’t experience this.</p>

<p>Generally, especially early in your career if you disagree with a comment ask the reviewer to explain it in person. 9/10 you’ll learn something new, the other 1/10 will be developers unaware there’s a new and maybe better way to do something - this is your time to shine! See a PR review as a learning experience and bear in mind that you too will think the code you’re writing now is terrible in a few years time.</p>]]></content><author><name>Edmund Steele</name></author><category term="software" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve now been a ‘self taught’ developer with 6 years professional experience. The process of reviewing graduate applications for my company has got me thinking about things that I’ve learnt coming into the industry and as I’ve gained more experience. I’ve got some groupings here that go beyond the non obvious stuff (know how to code)]]></summary></entry></feed>